Heat.
[Music]
Now you must have indication that uh we
recorded.
>> Oh yes.
and I I accept it
>> that I have finished here at the
American college anatia here in
so I can say that we both have u an
American I would say imprint in our side
inside ourselves
and um
uh I have your book yeah
>> ah thank you no I I didn't bought it
these days I have bought it uh when I
first find out about you
well and um uh
I heard that when you're entering the
langly
you say don't believe what you see. Is
that true?
>> When I enter langly
>> yeah uh it says a sign don't believe
what you see.
No.
>> Is that
>> he says uh I only regret that I have but
one life for my country.
>> Well, okay. So,
and um I have uh I have seen most of
your interviews and your presentations.
Uh I have seen your participation
on democracy now and um I'm I'm
following you all these two years or
three maybe I don't know when we became
friends
uh it came up I didn't know the
existence of you but I saw with Mr. the
papological interview. And I said,
>> I get
>> that was years ago.
>> Years ago.
>> And I said, "Oh, I didn't know that we
have a Greek guy working in things like
that." And then I start to uh follow
your uh your agony, I must say,
uh in in various issues, not only on uh
on things like moralities or your ex uh
work or things like that, but also about
democracy and about uh the dangers that
we we face in in our times. And I I I'm
I'm thinking that it is not only in the
USA that democracy is is on crisis. It
is also here in Greece and I do believe
also in Europe in various ways.
So uh please allow me. I have some uh
have wrote few things and then um
you can share your thoughts.
One thing that is u in times of crisis
it seems to be that is so thin the layer
of democracy
as it represents a system that creates
in the international um
uh labor uh international division of
labor and uh that uh
it seems that when the financial crisis
is actually arriving here in the in
various countries like uh USA like in
Greece it seems that uh this
worldwide in inequality that's creating
start eating the democracy also inside
of the of the original let's say he
hemonic countries like USA like Britain
like uh and um I was thinking that the
crisis of 1928
it was also a crisis of uh
democratic institutions in USA. It was
also almost a coup that was tried that
time. It was also uh an attempt of
assassination of President Roosevelt.
And um I was wondering if really you
think that uh democracy is facing
serious problems in USA and also in
countries that was uh uh adopted like
Greece for example.
Yeah, that's a good question and uh I
think the answer is definitely yes. I
think that democracy is is under threat
in the United States. You know, one of
the things that's that's always been a
mystery to me here is how few Americans
realize
how right-wing the country
uh for example, our Supreme Court is
very conservative and we've just uh
we've just banned for all intents and
purposes, we've banned abortion across
most of the country. Um now we're taking
uh books school system. uh because they
mentioned things like slavery uh for
example
slavery is a fact American history till
uh people own human beings here this is
something we can't just never happen uh
but in many uh state in the s United
States uh they ban any mention of
slavery they b any mention of of being
gay Okay. They ban me, right? We had
protests just yesterday because one of
our large military bases, Fort Bragg, uh
changed its name to Fort Liberty.
>> Uh now, Fort Bragg was named after a
general Bragg who was a southern general
in so he was a troop and he was a slave
owner and he's a racist. So why are we
honoring him by naming the largest uh
the largest military base in America
after him? And people protested because
they wanted to keep the name.
You know, we saw what happened on
January 6th. And uh the people who
participated in January 6 uh riots
>> are no less energized now. They really
believe that the election was stolen
from Donald Trump. they really wanted to
kill uh Nancy Pelosi uh and they would
do it again if they had the opportunity.
So I I believe that democracy is under
threat in the United States. It's under
threat from the right wing and it's
something that we have to all be attuned
to and aware of and to protect against.
>> Okay. Uh well I don't know it is one of
of my questions. Do you really think
that Donald Trump was so great danger
about uh United States um uh citizeny or
um it was um maybe a way to create
um a division inside of the country. Why
why I'm saying that I I was thinking
about the division in uh in in United
States
for example it is uh that I was hearing
for example in the
uh world economic forum various uh
participators during the Trump
presidency that was saying that USA will
stop to be uh I
the country that used to be as a power
as international power as the top power
in the world
and uh we see on these years that they
have passed in the last three years for
example that uh for example US dollars
has stopped or not stopped but has
limited as a currency.
>> Yes. first of all on um I think it's now
it's 47%
47 from 82 that was 60s for example on
the other hand it um
it seems that um
uh is it has gone in a war
that um
I don't know if we're going to live
again uh period as the second world war
here in Europe.
But um uh I was thinking that all these
um for example the green the green
energy uh the the price the cost of
having green energy that is um huge
comparing to conventional um like oil or
like petrol or like and that um also um
creates a huge uh um uh I don't know If
it is really uh it is a reality or not,
you will tell me. For the middle class
and for the poor people, life is seems
to be even more uh unbearable
for going forward. It looks like to me
there is middle class that is been
destroyed slowly if um especially after
the period of uh corona virus and um
always a democracy stands on the middle
class I mean as far as I know
and um this is the things that I'm
seeing and I'm saying well
it is really
They're trying to place United States
from the top most powerful country in
the whole world with its mistakes or
with its goods because nothing comes
straight good. But it really um it the
division that you are describing me is
helping because if United States get out
of the way it it would create a vacuum
phenomenon. Someone has to fill it
>> and honestly I wouldn't like for me
personally to be the Chinese.
>> Yes.
>> I think you understand what I mean.
>> So your thoughts on that?
>> Yes. I think that you've raised an
important point here and and this is in
part due to the shortsightedness
of US policy. Um you know an African
diplomat told me once when I was I was
in Africa still with the CIA. I I was
just visiting Africa and um he said you
know uh you Americans come here and you
promise us democracy but the Chinese
come here and they promise us food.
which one would you take? And it was to
me it was a way of really encapsulating
this whole issue in one sentence.
>> Mhm.
>> Um, one of the things that the United
States has has made serious mistakes
about is our reliance on the military.
We have a military budget of more than
$800 billion. Mhm.
>> That's more than the next nine largest
countries in the world combined.
>> Yep.
>> Well, as a result,
uh we don't give the kind a that the
Chinese Bel program uh calls for gives
the kind of that uh the provides. For
example, it's building the water system
in Yemen. uh we collect and we don't
even really do it cleanly
giving just the weapons we give credit
American defense contractors and that
recipient country uses those credits to
buy that but really we're just
subsidizing Mexican uh arms industry.
So
that's point number one. Number two is I
mentioned a minute of how conservative
this country is. One of the one of the
issues that comes out of that is that so
many Americans are against any form of
printing. They hate the idea of giving
away American taxpayer money to foreign
countries. Now without foreign aid,
why would any country want to do
anything to the United States? So when
we go to these countries and we say we
want you to vote this way in the United
Nations or we want you to join us in
Afghanistan or we want you to support us
in Libya. Why would they if we refuse to
give them anything? Now if we're not
giving them anything and the Chinese
are, who are they going to side with?
They're going to side with the Chinese.
You mentioned a moment ago how um
how many fewer international
transactions are using the dollar as the
uh as the international currency. That's
true. Uh just this year Saudi Arabia and
China made a bill for oil to be paid in
yuan.
>> The Kuwaitis made the same deal with
China to pay in yuan. uh where the money
pay in a basket of currencies that does
not include the dollar and includes all
the other major currencies. The Russians
since since uh the sanctions imposed on
the Russians following the invasion of
Ukraine, the Russians have been
insisting that everything u all all
their business deals be carried out in
equals and that's work.
Now we have the uh Brazilians, the
Argent, the Uruguay, possibly the
Chileans uh talking about uh uh a South
American euro for example.
>> Mhm.
>> Where they wouldn't need dollar anymore.
This to me is the is the the result of
poor planning when managing an empire.
All empires have an arc. The United
States is on the back end of that arc.
It's going down. And it's like we just
as a government, we just don't see it.
We don't see how we're denying ourselves
things. For example, I don't know if
you've ever been to the United States,
uh, Alexandre, but, uh, we have a we
have a a train system that we should be
embarrassed about.
>> We have second and third world airports
that that we should be embarrassed by
our airports. Our roads are a wreck. Our
bridges are falling into the rivers
below them because we spend all of our
money on wetlands. All of it. Yes. But
>> almost half of the entire budget is
spent on weapons.
>> Yes. But uh excuse me to interrupt you.
Um but after the second world war, the
the army industry was the base of uh the
development. I mean um that was the
reality uh that the arm industry became
the base of the American economy
development and things like that. And um
>> yes
>> and
I don't know it got even worse with the
the war in Ukraine and I was wondering
who wanted that war because it will
deepen the division inside the United
States. Let me ask you something.
Sometimes I think that let's say the
deep state or whoever is that is the
carrying the water for China in this
>> because Russia and China was never I
mean occasionally were in friendly
relationship during the history wiping
out Russia from the map or divided in
four pieces. Who is going to uh
guarantee that these four pieces will
not fail one after the other on the
Chinese regime influence? I mean, you
understand what I mean?
>> Yes. Yes. You're exactly right. You
know, it's it's funny because
much of the world for for exactly that
reason, I think much of the world feels
alone right now. Who do you trust? Who
do you rely with? is that the United
States, which as I said is on the back
side of that arc, you can't join with
the Russians. They have serious problems
of their own right now. And the Chinese,
the deal that the Chinese have been
giving everybody all these years with
aid is not as good a deal as everybody
thought it was. you know, the Africans.
We we had the um the president of the
Democratic Republic of the Congo here a
few a few months ago and uh and several
of us met this thing and he was that
they just don't they thought they
Chinese and now they trust the Chinese
because the Chinese came in with all
these ideas of of aid these very
generous ideas of aid and as it turns
out the Chinese have to take ownership
of everything and they he said Chinese
never meant to pay for ship with
offering the money
>> but they control
>> actually but they control most very
serious um economic problem that lasts
many years and one of the things that
they were forced to do was to sell
ownership of several of the major ports
like in Pa for example
>> and now you have the Chinese that are
playing
and I said you know that was supposed to
have been attemp were very thick. It was
supposed to have been to help the Greek
economy and it was an improvement of
relations between Greece and China. The
Chinese intend to stay there forever.
>> Of course,
>> maybe not militarily, but economically
>> and he said yes, but that's been
>> most of the rare earth mines are being
exploited by the Chinese
by the Chinese in Africa.
that is I mean uh has to do with semi
control with all these advanced
technology and things like that. It is a
it is under the Chinese how you say
operational
apparatus and that it is
>> you're exactly right
>> and
>> and they're smarter than the Americans
are.
>> I don't know if they're smarter. they're
more methodical and also no one can deny
that uh unfortunately for the United
States it was um the the the
way that have been treated sometimes the
third world it is a shameful way and um
I believe that that is one problem the
issue today something like we're going
to take a revenge of what uh you have
done both also the European uh north
countries that they used to be
excolonial
and now maybe it is the time they take
their revenge but you see United States
like it or not there was the guarant the
guaranter of uh democratic institutions
and that
it is in a period of jeopardizing
everything
Maybe it is not only I mean sometimes
when I see I will tell you exactly how I
see things and so um maybe I will be
more understandable to you.
For example,
it is like we've been forced here in
Europe to change all the prospect all
the way that we see human being.
transhumanism,
biomutation
[Music]
that it is something that they're trying
to force in every and no matter what
kind of culture you have, no matter what
kind of historical uh background you
have and it is it is I'm think
Darwinism for example as a platform
applied to socialist applied to neol
liberals applied to the communist
applied to the Chinese mauist and right
now it is like that it is not a matter
of humanity of democracy that the two or
three systems are fighting each other
each other. It is who will control this
kind of power or like technocracy power
with all these u
or whatever Mr. Har is mentioning and
who is going to control it and that I
that is the the kind of the two forces
or the three forces and right now in my
views I believe maybe because the
historical background of Russia. Russia
was not only a Soviet uh power. It also
was a terrorist power. It has a long uh
background in the history. It has
definitely a kind of culture that this
kind of movements need to eradicate this
kind of culture. And that is maybe the
reason that we have the war here in
Ukraine. I don't know. I'm sharing you
my thoughts because whatever happens
here with uh censoring for example
censoring is a huge problem no matter if
I'm speaking about Trump or if I'm
speaking about vaccine vaccinations or
whe I'm speaking about for example
agriculture production here in Europe
they are closing 3,000 farms in Holland
and they're forbid they pay of course
this this closing I mean uh these farms
and the farmers, but also they sign a
contract. They will never go again and
um
be farmer here in Europe or here in or
there in Holland. Some things are
changing forcibly
and really honestly because I'm a deeply
democratic. I believe that everyone
should have his opinion. Everybody I
don't I don't mind if you're gay or not.
It is not a matter of doesn't have to do
with me. It is up to your freedom.
Whatever you want to do. You understand
what I mean? And something is chasing in
huge force. And that change comes for
for example from the United States
embassy. It comes in from NATO. It comes
all these all these change are coming
not from uh someone behind the scenes.
you see it for example and that is
worrying me
and this is how I think about how I see
the things maybe I'm wrong
one of the things that people forget or
ignore and you you've made a a a good
point here
is how many moving parts are involved in
carrying out a foreign policy
uh because
Nothing really is bilateral. Everything
is multilateral. And this is something
that often times
even at the very high highest levels of
government, we don't recognize
and we don't plan for.
Uh we lament the fact here in the United
States that it's harder for us now to
maintain an empire
uh than it has been at at points in the
past. Uh that shouldn't be what the
conversation is. the convers the
conversations
how to the bar uh how promotes American
um
manufacturing and business abroad and
that's just not it's just not what we're
focused on and it's it's to the
detriment over the of of the United
States we're seeing it everywhere
we're seeing it with with countries for
example like or countries that are
friendly with us like Mexico for example
or Brazil telling us we don't want any
part of Ukraine more this is your
problem it's not our problem
uh we're seeing it
through for example when we vote and we
we complain about their human rights
practices then they respond to us by
saying what about what you're doing in
Yemen
you know you're the ones that sell the
Saudis and the Amiratis all the weapons
and the and the jet fighters that are
killing women and children. We're not
doing that. You're doing it.
And then we the third part of that, at
least in my view, is we also have um in
many cases poor leadership.
Um I know I know Tony Blinken. I worked
with Tony Blink on the Senate Foreign
Relations Committee. He's a very nice
man,
but he owes his entire adult life to Joe
Biden. every job he's ever had in his
life has been working for Joe Biden.
So, he's not the Secretary of State
because he's the smartest, most
forwardthinking
>> strategist
that the United States could identify.
And he's the Secretary of State because
he's been friends with Joe Biden for the
past 30 years and he's worked for him.
That's it.
You know, I had I had dinner with the
Russian not dinner, I had lunch with the
Russian ambassador a week ago yesterday
and we were talking about the foreign
minister Lavrov.
>> Mhm.
>> And I said, you know, when I was
assigned to the United Nations, uh,
Lavrov was the Russian ambassador to the
United Nations. And I said, uh,
all of us admired him because he was
such a good diplomat and he was working
with so much less than what the what the
other major western uh ambassadors were
working with, you know, the the the
ambassador Negroanti when I was there
and he had a a billion dollars budget
and the the might of the United States
behind him. You look at the British
ambassador, the French, the Chinese,
all of them had more than what Lapov
had. Yet he was seen as the the most
powerful, the most important, the most
strategic ambassador at the United
Nations. Well, why wasn't it the
American ambassador? Because the
American ambassador wasn't focused on
diplomacy.
the the American ambassador was focused
on on America's many wars uh around the
world and that catches up with us after
a while. After a while, other countries
begin to overtake us economically. The
Chinese, this belt and road thing has
been going on for decades. The Chinese
have been very deliberate and very quiet
about it.
>> Yeah.
>> They don't hold it in our faces
uh like we do military sales. everybody
else and look what's happened. They've
overtaked us.
So they were able to to work
better than we were.
>> Do you think that have influenced the
inside policy of United States
because I mean after uh
especially during Clinton and after the
Clinton presidency
the the relationship with China, United
States became so close. I mean on not
only culturally but uh only
technological advantages or uh things
like that. I mean all this breakup came
suddenly for example 2 years ago. Uh you
understand what I mean especially during
the presidential last presidential uh
elections of the United States. Suddenly
it appeared to be something hostile
a thing or a relationship that used to
be so sweet and cooperative.
>> Yes. Yes. And and let me add something
to that.
There are, no matter how bad things get
between the United States and China or
the United States and Russia,
they can still co-op
on in different areas. And I mentioned
this to the Russian ambassador.
I don't care how hot the war gets, we
can still cooperate on counterterrorism,
counter narcotics,
and counter proliferation.
We should be able to set aside other
differences in order to cooperate on
these issues that are important not just
for us but for everybody in the world.
And I said when I was stationed in
Afghanistan, one of the things that I
learned very very early on was that
Afghanistan produces 93%
of the world's heroin
>> and almost all of that heroin Yes.
>> almost all of that heroin goes to Russia
and Iran. They have the highest heroin
addiction rates in the world.
Well, the United States has a heroin
problem, too. And this is an area where
we can we can cooperate that has nothing
to do with politics and it has nothing
to do with fighting a hot war.
>> Now, let me make like make a question
now.
>> Mhm.
>> Before uh
before Taliban take the power
20 years ago,
they have eradicated. No, after the
Taliban took power, they have eradicated
>> Afghanistan used to be the producer of
uh popay and urine of 80% of the world
production. They diminished to 5% as far
as I remember and then suddenly a war
begins in Afghanistan and then I'm
seeing photos and I don't know if the
photos are real or not. I see British
and American soldiers
guarding the pop uh the popey
fields and I say
>> yes
>> well this war was happen did happen to
protect the production or you understand
what I mean I mean you know that uh
>> and and I'll I'll add something to that
I went to Afghanistan in 2011
when I was with the Senate Foreign
Relations Committee. John Kerry was the
chairman and I went to do a study on
heroin uh production.
So I flew to Bram Air Base and they make
a helicopter
to the village of Lashbar
in Telman.
And so
I said, I I want to talk to a um a puppy
farmer. Her poppy. Oh, that's a very bad
idea. I said, no, no, it's important for
my study. I have to do this. So we drove
out to Lasha
and we see a farmer out in the field
taking care of his puppy and we got out.
It was Jeeps, four or five jeeps,
and I had a translator with me.
So,
we were talking and I said to him, and
it it's funny in retrospect. It wasn't
funny at the time, but now it's funny. I
said, "Why don't you grow things that
have two growing seasons like onions or
pomegranates or tomatoes
>> to eat?"
>> It goes like this.
He said, "The Americans told me in 2001
that if I told them where the Arabs were
hiding, I could grow all the poppy I
wanted. And now you come here and you
tell me I can't grow poppy."
>> You're pulling my leg. And
>> I said, I said, "What American told you
you could grow poppy?"
And my military handler said, "That's
it. We have to go. It's too dangerous
here. We have to go. Everybody in the
jeeps."
So I put in my report I believe the
American military is protecting the
puppy farmers. I don't know why,
>> you know,
>> but they're doing
>> I will tell you something. Taking in
account for example on World War II uh
CIA or OSS at that time.
>> Yes.
>> Uh it was it has a close relationship
with the Italian mafia. So Oh yeah.
>> They could help them and did help them
to make um uh the take the taking of
Sicily.
>> Yes. And then after the after after OSS
turned to CIA, we see that uh the
American mafia because it didn't have
the ability to rebuild its empire
>> in United States, it built it to Kuba.
>> Yeah. And we see that on the background
mafia and CIA cooperating helping Sam
samosa I think was the
>> years
>> and now you know it was also with Oliver
North the Iran Iraq gate contrast uh
scandal. It seems to be that we see
something but also underneath or maybe
on the black oper black operations, not
all the CIA maybe a part of it but a
very strong one is going along with the
international drug cartel or you know
uh it puzzles me many times when I I
read this contradictions between war
against drugs and the other hand. I mean
it was something very serious concerning
Mexico or Escobar and then I'm finding
out the following thing that Escobar was
keeping so much real money
32 billion US in various areas when
United States had printed $200 billion I
mean he was keeping
real money you understand about money
fragmentation and that was a huge
problem I I mean he was creating let's
say inflation in the United States
because you don't print the money that
is circulating you're printing only part
of it a fragment much and and then of
course you're going to take out Escobar
you know because he has literally
one one tenth or whatever it was this 33
billion that time I mean was huge real
money and he said
>> the actual actual cash
>> the actual cash and I it. Okay. Did was
I mean was this the reason that they
took out Escobar and they brought uh on
the front the Cali
cartel
gentlemen of Kali.
>> Yes. When you are you know this is the
way that I'm reading history and this is
why I enjoy so much that I'm now I'm
talking with you and this is it's
getting possible. I mean what is real
and what is not real? What is true and
what is not true. So what your thoughts
are on that?
>> Well,
people have asked me that question many
times over the years, and there's a
there's an easy answer, but it's a
little bit cynical.
Um, the United The CIA
has never cared about drugs. They don't
care at all. They don't care if
everybody in the world is addicted to
drugs. For most of their existence, they
cared about communism.
They wanted to stop communism. And if
they could if they could convince the
communist rebels in Colombia or
Venezuela to help them,
>> then
>> cultivate as much cocaine you want. We
don't mind.
What the hell? They don't there there's
a there's a television series here in
the United States on Netflix. Maybe you
saw it. It's called Nars.
>> Yeah, of course I saw it. Yeah.
>> Well, you know, it it's written from DA
perspective.
And China says they're going to go catch
Pablo Escob just as they're going to
catch the Ki cartel. the station is
chief is there and he
up the whole
>> freeze it. Yeah.
>> Those those were his troops
and it's because this guy this cartel
to communist rebel
they don't care that that's the EA.
>> Okay, listen. Let me ask something now.
What is the Okay, you're not cynical.
You are immoral. It's not just totally
different because when you fight
communism for example like what I mean
is the strangulation or the how you say
whatever is strangling human liberty you
are standing from a high moral point.
>> Yes.
>> Okay. And so you you should serve this
kind of values and morality. If you are
uh sabotaging these things and then it
is it is logical that it's going to okay
it's going to influence you is what will
corrupt you eventually I think
>> yes yes and you have to ask what kind of
country do you want to be do you want to
be the shining beacon of hope for
democracy and civil rights and civil
liberties and human rights or do you
not? Do you want to be the arms dealer
that allows for trafficking in
trafficking because of your obsession
with communism? You have to ask what
kind of country because you can't be
both. It has to be one. The United
States has never made that that choice.
They want to be both.
They want to go embassy to embassy and
tell people you need to respect human
rights and you need to respect the
rights of the minorities and you need to
respect religious tolerance and then at
the same time we have secret prisons and
torture programs and assassination squad
kidnapping teams.
>> You're talking about which you're
talking about um the secret services of
in the United States. I don't know if
it's about C or CIA or about FBI. You're
talking about that kind of operators
existing.
>> No, I'm talking I'm talking about things
that the CIA does where another example
there's a life example.
>> Um
I was working in a Middle Eastern
country and um
I was a human rights officer.
>> Human human. Human. You were human. uh
>> rights officer.
>> Ah human rights officer. Okay.
>> So it was my job at the embassy to
monitor human rights of that country and
I had to write reports for 30 years.
>> Okay.
>> So uh there was a pro-democracy
demonstration. The police arrested a
15year-old boy and they took him to the
police station and they beat him to
death. They killed him. And then they
called his father and said to the police
station and pick up the bot.
>> Okay.
>> So I went to see the minister of of
interior and I said, "Your highness, you
cannot you cannot beat a 15-year-old to
death for participating in a
pro-democracy march, a peaceful
demonstration." I said, "I I have to
report this to Congress, and this may
your your arms purchases from us." They
were buying F-16s at the time.
15 minutes later, I leave and the CIA
station chief come for a meeting and he
says, "Don't listen to what the human
sky is telling you. We want you to open
a prison for us so we can torture people
here. or better, you torture me and then
you give us a report of that they say
and we'll give you $100 million.
So who is he going to listen to? Is he
going to listen to me or is he going to
listen to the station?
>> Were you always a ramblefist?
>> Say that again.
>> Were you were always a ramblefist or it
came as you were growing up?
>> You know what?
Really? I mean, that's a good question.
>> No, it was not not when I was growing
up. I was always I was always the good
boy. I was always the one who want to be
adults and do the right thing and get
good grades and go to good school and
get a good job happily ever after.
>> Mhm. And then I got to the point where,
you know, I got to the CIA and I started
to see things that were happening and I
thought to myself, this is wrong, wrong,
wrong. This is against the law. It's a
violation of human rights. Somebody has
to say something. So I waited. Who's
going to say something? And then nobody
says anything. I'll give you another
example. The night that we captured Abu
Buba in Farabad Pakistan.
>> Mhm.
>> We caught
dozens dozens.
>> It was 14 houses different attack as I
remember. Yeah.
>> There were so many al-Qaeda be caught
like we put keep them all in the safe
house. So we put them all in the jail in
fab and we were bringing them to the
safe house 10 at a time for
interrogation. Well, the first group of
10 came in and one of my colleagues
brought them in and they all had hoods
on. Their heads were covered and I
said,"Wh do they have hoods on?"
And he said, "We don't want them to see
our face."
I said, "Are you seriously telling me
that you have never read the Geneva
Convention? You can't put hoods on them.
It's a war crime. Take those hoods off."
And he said, "If you take those hoods
off, I'm going to report you to
headquarters."
And I said, "Oh, I'm going to report you
to headquarters for committing a war
crime. Take those hoods off." And I
pulled the hoods up. We reported each
other to headquarters.
And I got in trouble.
>> Of course you got to get in trouble. Are
you serious? Of course you will be the
one going to be man. No.
really I mean okay I I I I don't I I see
that no I know I have sense that you're
a really smart person I don't I don't
believe that you are naive and uh I
believe that also the training that you
get when you're working for such huge um
so famous um
company or whatever how you going to
call it it's a it's something really
beyond the limits of of an average
person I'm not I'm not saying that
everyone has to be genius but you have
to be above average in many ways to
handle things on uh on a field. Okay,
maybe on as an analyst just need your
brain. You don't need the the other
things. But anyway, so it is it is
surprising me that I mean really
surprised me because first of all the
Geneva Convention is about uh how you
say recognized
uh combat combatant.
It's not about that kind of prisoners.
So and uh also uh you know I have I have
found out the manual of enhaggation
and I
you know I read it all.
It was surprising me. Uh you do that uh
water broading for example, how you call
it? Water
>> water boarding.
>> Yeah. 10 seconds and then 20 seconds you
leave it and then you can do it twice a
week for example and you can do it I
mean
you're going to keep a guy in a cold
water so this minutes this and this is
how many times you can do it that and
you can do it no not the next week the
week after I mean it was huge
sophisticated scientific analysis on the
ability of the human body to take to the
limit and and break it. Amazing.
It's amazing. I don't know. Um maybe
I don't know maybe when you're fighting
u
terrorists that you have created I mean
taking advantage taking in account that
al-Qaeda was created by the United
States. Maybe you have to this kind of
methods.
>> Um
>> uh I don't know. Do you think that they
are they keep working and and using this
uh manual?
>> I I think probably no. Uh only because
the the the real answer is we don't
know. Nobody knows.
>> Nobody knows. I think probably no
because
at the very end of the Obama
administration, President Obama ordered
that the CIA respect the rules that were
laid out in the Army Field Manual.
>> Mhm.
>> And the Army Field Manual says he do
>> and what you can't do and this is how
you have to do it. That's that's great.
But the Army Field Manual is an
executive branch document. And so
the executive branch, the office of the
president, they can change the rules
anytime they want.
>> Mhm.
>> And they can classify the change so that
>> so that the rest of us don't know it's
been changed.
So I like to think that
that we're not pushing people more like
we do
but I I don't know that that's the case
>> because this I think this is what you
have paid I mean
on your 23 months it was 23 months
finally I mean it is fun it is a funny
book in many ways yeah a really good one
I didn't read the other
I didn't read the other one that you had
right the reluctant uh spy.
>> No, I didn't read. I mean, why you read
it? I have it here with me.
Spies like us.
So, can I ask you a few questions about
uh
17th of November?
>> Sure.
>> Okay.
Now few days ago I don't know if you it
came to your attention uh was uh a guy
that he was working with um
Richard WS at that time that he wrote a
book about uh the assassination.
>> Yes. And
yeah.
>> Yeah. And uh
because of my
nature, I was always
reading and analyzing
anything that had to do with 17th of
November.
And um so let me see the question how
have uh how I have write it because it
has to be in a way that you can probably
answer it.
There is an extensive
um extensive number of books and
articles
that connect for example Brigati Rosi
with uh with secret services
especially because of the assassination
of Aldor.
So I um I I sometimes I have asked
myself and I will give you the reasons
that I am asking
um that probably a part of 17th of
November was actually working knowing or
not knowing for um
um for secret services. Why I say that?
There are some assassinations
that actually looks like clean some uh
uh competition. For example,
we are cleaning an old card of people
like in the press or on the arm dealing
and creating a vacuum that will be
fulfilled later by new incomers of that.
and uh all that contracts
under the I say
let's say we do it because we are
anti-Americans we are anti- capitalist
and we are doing what our moral Yeah.
Okay. Now
as I was reading the murder the
assassination of Mr. with Richard Wells.
When I read the unauthorized biography
of George Bush,
it was for surprise for me that in a
period of month,
first of all, George Bush became uh
director of Central Agency.
>> Yes. uh breaking the
what the Democrats wanted didn't want
him because I think there were some
checks that were being found on the
hands of those the burglars of the
Watergate
that were coming from a Bush company and
also dissolve the the two uh
Pike and Church Commission that not only
were looking about uh the whereabouts of
CIA but also they were on the procedure
to impeach Mr. Kiser.
>> Yeah.
>> So and that happened in a month and also
I read that he was buried in the
Arlington cemetery something that has to
do with the military not with officers
of um no matter who we were. And then
and then I I really asked myself is
something that we can see as quibono
that it means that
did they use create did you know
cooperation with gates you know I mean I
have read few uh for example how huch
took out from uh Soviet Union it was a
cooperation between uh the United States
secret service KGB because KGB gave the
the memor the memor of
uh and then they were printed here in uh
in the west and then uh they they
imported back to so so the Russian
people to know what is styism stalinism
is about. So I so I said brutally I said
to myself and uh really thought
did they been used by the secret
services
also is the way how they how they were
caught up and
>> yeah this is my first question if you
can answer answer I don't know
>> I'm sorry
>> you probably saw in the book that the
night that uh that Welch was killed,
one of the CIA officers had to be
physically restrained, held back because
he wanted to go to the Russian embassy
and kill the KGB residant.
>> Mhm.
>> Um so in the in the beginning in when I
say beginning, I mean just those first
few days after Welch was killed,
>> Mhm.
>> there was a school of thought. This was
the KTB, the headsets. The Russians
reached out to us and they said,
"Listen, promise it us."
Now, in Sikko that night, there just
happened to be a man walking his dog
when Welch was killed.
I found
in 1998.
He was the Bulgarian.
>> He was the Bulgarian. Okay.
>> The Bulgarian
and I went to knew him
and he said he heard the shot but he
didn't know him from and then he thought
oh it must
he said but I can hear you. It was
>> it was not us. And then I went to
Romania other CIA officers. The
Romanians, the Bulgarians,
um, both opened us, just open them, come
look at anything we want. So we took
some translation from CIA headquarters.
We looked at everything they had. There
was no involvement of secret services.
And then of course you know in the days
after both killing
>> you know the whole story with uh Jean
Partra and and
>> yeah it's a famous story now
and that's when you started looking you
know I I'll tell you that
from 1975 from December 23rd 1975 until
until
1999,
>> we had probably 5,000 names in our CIA
databases
>> of possible vehicity members because we
didn't we didn't know who was in this
group.
>> Their security was so good. They were so
secretive in their position. So out of
all the names,
we had like three of them right and the
others were mystery to us.
>> Okay.
>> But even with the ones that we had,
right, just didn't know where they were.
I'm getting a little bit ahead of
myself. The bottom line is it was a only
a very short period of time that we
thought secret services were involved in
Welch's killing. We believed the
Russians when when they told us they had
nothing to do with it. You see, because
we had an agreement with the Russians,
you don't
understandable.
>> Yeah. You don't kill our people, we
won't kill your people. It was as simple
as that.
>> And that's why we were able to to
operate in the same city at the same
time for all those decades because we
had agreed like gentlemen that we would
not kill each other. So they came to us
immediately and said, "We promise it was
not us."
>> And then, you know, as we did the
investigation,
um, there was no evidence that the
Russians were involved.
>> Just nothing.
>> I didn't mean that the Russians were
involved. I I I meant if it was an
inside job because
>> Oh, no. No. The CIA doesn't do that. We
We hear that a lot. You know, the the
inside job.
>> Question. the uh you know you kill your
own people to to what's the French word
for it? It's a provocator.
>> Oh yeah. All right.
>> Um now we don't do it
>> because
>> we would rather kill somebody else.
>> Of course.
>> I know you have to kill me after we
finish that conversation.
Well, uh because I I mean the first
question that came in my mind it was the
how did they know who was the CIA
controller in
>> oh no that's the easy one
>> I mean how do you know the face I mean
what he's saying because this is not a
kind of a a tip or information you can
find it you don't you don't know now I
mean how about
>> no it was different then the CIA had an
officer who got broke. His name was
Philip Ag.
>> Philip Ag,
>> right? So, Philip AG published uh a
Clipper Action newsletter it called and
he listed the names of all of the
>> He was also Richard Welsho that he
worked with. That's right.
>> Okay.
>> And um Welch's name was there. Welch's
name was up by a Greek newspaper that
published it. M this paper no longer
exists and I can't remember the name of
it. Um but anyway they published the
name and they published the address and
uh when Welch first moved he came from
Chile and when he first moved to Gree
>> Chile or Peru
Chile or Peru?
>> Uh Peru. Peru. Thank
>> you. And uh they asked him if he wanted
to move to to France.
>> He said no. This was a beautiful house.
The embassy had owned it for many years.
He's just going to move into that house.
So, it was the information was easy to
find. People knew where the CIA station
chief lived. It was the information was
up there. And I'll tell you the crazy
thing is the American embassy still owns
that house
that the Marines the Marine offices
who work in the embassy all live in that
house. Oh,
>> and on the day that I moved to Athens,
they said, "We're going to put you in
Nordine's house in
>> Kician."
>> I said, "Absolutely not."
Beautiful house and we own it. They said
they found his head on the roof of house
next door. And you want me to move into
that house?
>> It's a haunted house. Absolutely
not.
>> But you don't think that uh well, okay,
it was not uh of foreigner secret
services. I don't know. But it it looks
like they were making contracts. And I
will tell you something someone told me
here in Greece.
Okay, maybe it's true, maybe it's not
true.
I believe that there was no reason to
lie to me. But he told me the day that
we killed Baguyanis, assassinate
Baguyanis,
Bakuanis uh gave a phone call to his
secretary to her secretary
that he going to pass by office instead
of go straight to Bullin to take an
envelope.
Uh
so
the next day from the send from the
Greek intelligence services they heard
the phone call.
So they thought
how who could know
that he will pass from his office and
not go straight to the bullying? who had
the ability to hear him in the same time
I mean you know real time because at
that time they they didn't have the
ability to um to intercept the call in
real time they was taking the tapes in
there and
and um you know I mean you thinking all
right how did they know and the place
who was I don't know
this is
>> but don't forget get too that that one
of the things that was very very good at
was long-term surveillance. They would
follow people for a month or longer.
>> But this means an organization with 100
people. I mean, it's not a matter of one
or two.
>> Oh, no. I I know. I I get it. But they
were they were very good at being able
to change their plans quickly.
um and to and to and to drug plans. We
got a call when I was in Greece in 1999.
Uh the the American ambassador was uh
Nicholas Burns.
>> Yeah.
>> Um Bert got a call from uh one of the
shipping families
and um and he said uh I love and I I
want your help.
So several of us met with him in his uh
golden
and uh I'm I'm deep followed. I see the
same man watching my apartment. I
followed my car. So we took all the
information and we said you should be
you should be greed and and stay with me
for four, five or six weeks.
So we took the information, we gave it
to AP and we gave it to the uh the
and he left for Switzerland. He stayed
Switzerland um for 6 weeks.
>> The license plates that he got were all
stolen. All of them. Mhm. And we were
never able to find people that were
doing this. But we were convinced that
this was that they were going to kill
him. He was just alert to it.
>> Yeah, of course. I understand.
>> And um and it saved him. Now, what they
did with Bakuani
um
you know, they hit him in the lofty the
apartment building
>> and then they went over the hill into
there's such there's such chaos at the
time. Even though he wasn't supposed to
be there at that time, he normally
wouldn't be there at that time.
>> They were used to people being aware of
their aware of their surroundings and
changing their plans and then adjusting
to the changes.
>> Isn't Isn't that uh John isn't that
huge? I mean, it is not a matter of
five, six, seven people. It is something
that has a whole organization being
expertise, being trained. I mean,
>> oh no, no, no. You'd be surprised. When
I was when I was surveillance at the
CIA, we never had missions, Steve.
Never. It's It's too alerting. I will
tell you one story that I think you'll
like.
>> I was talking once to a French
intelligence officer.
>> Mhm.
>> And he told me that he was doing
surveillance on an Iranian nuclear
scientist.
>> Okay. and he said this nuclear scientist
was very well trained by the Iranian
intelligence services.
>> So
all day long as he's walking around
Paris, he's going like this to look
behind him.
He said that the French had 50 people
all walking towards him and then they
would boop around
>> and come again.
But he's so worried about who's behind
him.
>> He didn't see who is in front of him.
>> He never looked to see who's in front of
him. He said they followed him
everywhere. Everywhere. So there are
ways to do it with a lot of people.
There are ways to do it just a few
people. It's much easier if you only
have four.
>> Of course, the whole I mean the whole
story of the Gan is very impressing
impressive impressive. I mean all these
years been not uh in the dark doing all
these uh different kind of
assassination. I mean they have killed
any kind of people. They have killed
military officers. They have been
diplomatic officers. They have killed
political
opponents. They have killed press
owners. I mean it is not they have
killed anything that they were
targeting. I don't know. So I thought
that uh so you don't think that there
were a contract between uh them and
someone that was u benefit from this
kind of uh
>> no but there were contracts between them
and other groups. Uh there was
cooperation with Ella and of course the
uh the connection between Deafa Nobody
and Ella was
Christo
>> he was the only person that we were able
to identify who moved from
>> Mhm.
>> Um so Tutu was was a bad guy but there
was cooperation with Carlos the Jack
>> with
>> uh the Carlos the Jacko
>> Carlos the Jacko. Yeah.
>> Yeah. There was cooperation with Carlos.
There was cooperation with the Irish
Republican Army. There was cooperation
with the Libyan government, with the
Palestinian factions,
>> PLO, the Palestinian factions, but but
not much. We saw much more of that with
Ella was very happy to reach out to
different groups and do training
together and cooperate. And
>> they were more open. I mean, after all,
they were more
>> Yeah. uh more in activism as I must say.
>> Yes.
>> Do they have any political affiliations?
We always believed that they did and in
the end we never find any
but we always believed that there that
there was some sort of we just could
never
vanish many things in the hales.
>> It's a fascinating is it?
>> Yeah of course it is fascinating. It's a
fascinating because also Islams let's
say we have um for example till that
time till the trial of the gan
uh we could understand what means
political activism of course you don't
go and kill someone
>> uh but uh it took also inside like a
2000 patriot 2001 uh your patriotic uh
how you call it uh patriot act.
>> Yeah.
>> So it took inside things that could do
without harming others. You understand
what I mean? Patriotic act was very
tight. I mean you what you want freedom
or security whatever. So after the trial
of uh and during the trial of the of
17th November things on on political
perspective have been start been
getting tired and uh very easy
stigmatizing you.
>> Mhm. Mhm. And uh this is going even
worse and our time
uh as a as a seed
and this is the reason that I I mean I
wanted to ask you if from your
experience
>> well who you should talk to. Have you
ever spoken to Brady Keley?
>> I have been exchanged emails with him
about two years ago. one year ago we
have exchange emails because I wanted uh
he he has a huge archive of
>> that's huge you know I was saying I was
going to I wanted to write a book about
that
>> so I happened to be in Athens I don't
remember why I was in Athens it was like
I took my children or something and I
had lunch with Brady and uh he gave give
me a copy of his book. He said, "Oh, I
heard you're going to write a book about
17 November." I said, "I'd like to. I've
been thinking about it and I' I've been
accumulating a lot of information." But
my problem is the CIA, they don't want
me to say anything. I think he's
blacking everything out.
>> So then I read his book
>> and I wrote him a No. And I said,
"Picky,
I can't I can't write a book now."
>> You have read everything.
You would
>> you my
>> your hook is so good I can't keep
>> well okay you you have so many I mean I
believe you have so so many
things that you have done so far and uh
all this experience accumulated uh
although that you are very young
>> thank you I will I think I'm probably
>> don't worry you're still young
and I think it is a how do you say a
future in front of you do you think that
we are in um changing the subject that
two things more that I want to ask you
if you have time
do you think that uh we are in the edge
of a nuclear war
>> I don't this is a question that comes up
in Washington every day people are
genuinely worried about a nuclear war
but I think So um we I talked to the
Russian last week and he said that
that uh the Russians are not fools.
>> The Russians
>> they know that the Russians are not
fools. He said that they know they
understand
of using it. And he said I would remind
you the only country on earth that has
nuclear weapons is the United States.
And I said, "No, I expect but we we've
heard lessons from here
and we we know not to ever do this
again." But he says that the Russian
government has a longstanding no policy
and uh that they will not use nuclear
weapons. Yes.
>> And I said, "What about tactical nuclear
weapons?"
>> Yeah. For example,
>> or depleted uranium weapons as it
happened.
>> Exactly.
Exactly. And he said that the depleted
growing weapons are American that we
don't really
>> Yeah. And the tactical nuclear weapons
the only the only place that we're
seeing Russian tactical nuclear weapons
is in the American press.
So I hope he's right. I I think he
probably is. I don't see any benefit to
be using nuclear weapons.
>> Who's going to benefit from that? But
you know when you have I'm not talking
about the Russians right now. uh I'm not
taking them out of the equation but
I have okay I have a theory everyone has
you know a theory but
I see that
the how do you call it uh the financial
sector of the west
is on crumble during the stock market
bubble whole casino
and
all this is getting in a as you're
failing and failing and everything is
coming tight and you need something to
escape.
It happened on the first world war.
The financial system wanted to escape.
It happens also in the second world war.
The financial system wanted to escape
and keep of course all that inequality
in a global on a global basis. And this
is what the war it wore me because if
people like have you you have described
that naivity or not so bright or not so
being able to look far forward and you
understand seeing only what is in front
of me and uh I do I I do u I do worry
about that prospect I mean that these
people that have I mean 1% has u I don't
3,000 people owns 13 billion trillion US
and it's huge.
It is it really huge. Vanguard and Black
Row controls 23 trillion. Uh you know a
huge assets that have been accumulated
all these last 20 years, 30 years
or more in very few hands
and they're struggling
the real economy
and they're trying
this is what how I say maybe I'm totally
wrong. It is like they're trying to
escape through the war through
distraction is a very um it is not the
first time that the things think things
like that happening. It happens before
it really gets wor because
rich people don't have any kind. This is
the I mean they are cynicals.
They don't give a damn about anything
else
>> but to keep the riches.
>> So this is why what is worrying me. I
mean, you know, we have here in uh we're
in uh in Europe, we are in a way of
demonstr
industrialization.
We are in a a demographic crisis. USA
also is in demographic crisis.
>> Okay. Uh so I mean
they are asking us uh for for example
green energy when we are getting fewer
and fewer and fewer and let's say for
example in Greece if we're 11,000 11
million for example our depth for every
head is less if we getting now 9 million
it's double the depth on every head I
mean it's coming even more difficult to
get out of this spiral equation and
for for example the the European economy
is been based on Germany.
Germany was the the heart the pump of
everything when it collapsing it
collapse also the the Greek economy
whatever left from it. So this is the
reason that I made this question
and if you have something in your mind.
>> Yeah, I it's a good point. It's I I
don't disagree with you. I think this is
uh
it's a it's a problem that's not unique
to the United States certainly or even
to Europe. Um
>> it is like someone is driving us
to the bottom.
>> Yes. And I see the forces that are huge.
I I'm not a conspirator but I see really
I see forces. I mean I see like the the
World Economic Forum for example. It's a
huge I mean
>> who is going to ask the European the the
World Economic Forum to say it is not an
democratic institution. It is not be
elected. there's uh 5,000 of most uh
influenced people around the world. So
this is some something like really I I I
have that feeling that someone is is
taken from here and is taken on the
bottom of the maybe I don't know what is
your feeling on that.
>> No, I I think you've hit it on the head.
I think that that's I think you're
exactly right. I I'm not sure I could
even add anything.
>> Okay. And the last question for you.
>> Mhm.
>> It is well known that during the cold
war CIA had created and fought also a
cultural war. Popart a vanguard.
She funded leftist newspapers, magazine,
people from the socialist parties,
socialist parties like uh Spain,
Portugal, Italy, I mean whatever.
>> Yes. Now
I see that the war culture and forgive
me is been promoted by the American
embassy for example.
>> Yeah.
>> The gay parade uh pride parades or
whatever.
Um
and I really all this cultural change on
the prospect I have also mentioned
before trans human the sexuality of the
children sexualization of the children I
don't know what is your opinion on this
but it seems that comes from formal
platforms I mean platforms of power
and it is a it is um how in heaven
civil
how you say civil storm you know
>> how I see it that it's taking everything
under it you cannot I mean you cannot
fight back
so what's your
>> yes yes you you are absolutely right
about this this is a constant complaint
from other uh countries uh about the
United States forcing its own um moral
and ethical standards on other
countries. Uh
you know, you know how hard it is if
you're an American embassy officer and
you're going you go to another
government and you say, "Look, you know,
we want you to to to uh vote uh yes on
this United Nations Security
Resolution." Okay, that's your job. But
then you know how hard it is to go to
that same government and say we want you
to vote yes on gay marriage or we want
you to vote yes on on trans uh medical
care for trans children.
>> Yeah that is that is not
anybody should have medical uh uh care
no matter if you are trans or not but
when you are children I mean think
yourself if you are 4 years old or 8
years old the world is a fantasy it's
not a reality. Exactly.
And and that's where we get into trouble
pushing social to another country.
>> Yes.
>> So you agree that is a the same but it's
a copy copy paste of uh the cold war
era.
>> Oh yes very much so. But then it's it's
romantic now to think it is
>> it's romantic to think back on the 1950s
and the 1950s when we were taking Dr.
and translating Russia and working with
the smuggling into Russia.
>> That's very romantic. They make these
things.
>> But no, if you don't think about things
that it's deep is cutting edge culture
issues.
>> Yes.
>> And we can get in trouble with this.
Well, I I I I
think from the bottom of my heart,
please
Heat. Heat.
Heat.
[Music]
Heat. Heat.